[Music]
thank you
hello greetings good evening good day
everybody and welcome to the awesome
show we have gone past 150 episodes we
are in into episode 151 and it's all
thanks to you so thank you so much for
supporting the show yes
um and as always we have a whole bunch
of questions the number of questions is
going on increasing week after week I'm
getting a flood of questions every week
so once again thank you for that so
before we get into it as always let me
greet you all let's see who all is there
on the live chat and let's take a look
at that I can say geopolitical Dube I
can say
rtkpush Roma Bliss Nero harshit
the Green Arrow uh shibin sugartan Giga
whatever
mystery man of manohar Abhishek Joshi
Harwood butcher k-89911
[Music]
flying Raven and so many other people
Illuminati Creek bikash manav flying
Raven xkg agent General sriram
nikhilworth Karan riju solanki Suman and
everybody else thank you so much for
being on the show thank you so much I
really appreciate it and now let's get
into the questions what are the
questions that we have today I will try
and answer as many of these as possible
as always I get so many questions every
week and I'm really grateful for that
but I can only pick a few so please
don't get upset if I have not picked
your question please don't get emotional
about it I try and pick the most in uh
interesting questions that I can see and
hopefully it uh it provides value to all
of you right let's go into the questions
and this is not a question it's from AV
it's a shout out to Hockey World Cup
please yes so there's a Hockey World Cup
going on right now in odisha in Roar
killer and uh
um
yeah well it's in in this region that
the the hockey World Cup has been being
played and unfortunately there's not
much coverage of it in the Indian media
as always the Indian media is obsessed
with only one sport cricket and only one
entertainment industry Bollywood so uh
do Please be aware that's there's a
Hockey World Cup going on I personally
am a huge fan of hockey I think hockey
is a really really interesting sport
it's a really fast paced export I can
never sit and watch hockey I'm like
especially when my team is playing India
you know I get really involved in that
and I think there was a match going on
just now between India and the old enemy
England so I'm not sure what happened in
that I was busy with other things I
could not see it but yes be aware that
there's a World Cup on and let's support
our team and let's support this sport
hockey which I believe is India's
national sport so shout out to the
hockey World Cup yes indeed
okay let's go to the next question
it's my son hi I'm from Pakistan India
as a big brother should lend a helping
hand to Pakistan in return Pakistan can
give India a space a safe route to
Central Asia we should help each other
for a good future well you know it's
it's really good to see that there are
sensible people on both sides of the
Border you know we typically see the the
india-pakistan relationship from a very
specific perspective from a very
specific lens and obviously we cannot uh
ignore the history that we've had the
the forcible partition of India by
external actors by by Foreign occupiers
who who cut India into pieces before
they left India it was a terrible
partition very bloody and then there
there have been four Wars that have been
fought between India and Pakistan and so
that's the that's the terrible history
that we have you know and like it or not
everybody sees the relationship through
that perspective
and in in the the media obviously does
its bit to uh keep the tensions high and
all that but it's good to see that there
are sensible voices on the Pakistani
side on India in India size as well so
uh the thing is yeah it would be great
if if we could get along peacefully
let's let's take a look at the map to
understand I'm sure everybody knows the
India Pakistan uh
map but let's anyway take a look at it
so what is Asana suggesting
uh there we are the India Pakistan thing
so uh so he's suggesting that India
should lend a helping end to Pakistan in
return in Pakistan can give India a safe
route to Central Asia So currently the
the route to Central Asia is is cut off
yeah it is it is uh is cut off because
Pakistan currently occupies temporarily
what we call Pakistan occupied Kashmir
right so that's the situation right now
and that is the situation that's been
there since 1948.
is suggesting to work out Pakistan would
have to uh return this territory to
India Pakistan occupied Kashmir that's
what would need to happen and then we
can see how things go right and there is
no sign of that happening so what needs
to happen is that a stable safe
Democratic and peaceful government needs
to come into power in Pakistan right now
Pakistan is ruled by the Pakistani army
and there's a puppet government that's
in place yeah uh the the whoever is the
prime minister of Pakistan at any given
point in time is never really in power
the true power always has resided in the
hands of the Pakistani army the Pakistan
Armed Forces yes uh so that's the
situation so I I would be really happy
if India and Pakistan could get along
peacefully and then there would be no
need to ever indulge in a future War
right
uh but for that Pakistan has to become
truly Democratic Pakistan has to uh the
people of Pakistan need to take back
power from the Pakistani army which
which forcibly occupies the country yeah
and then this border dispute needs to be
resolved we know that there have been
massive protests going on in Pakistan
Kashmir they want reunification with
with India yeah we know that's happening
so if that happens then India will
regain its its uh land connectivity with
Afghanistan and through Afghanistan to
Central Asia and if Pakistan gives up
its its uh
uh its desire to have to to wage
continuous never-ending war with India
then we could get along in peace and
there would be no need for any animosity
any future War any of those things yeah
so I think unfortunately uh the ball
lies in Pakistan's Court
the ball lies in Pakistan's Court India
has never initiated any of the uh any of
the hostilities that the Pakistan India
ever had in the past right we've have we
have fought four wars in the past and
each of these four Wars has been
initiated unfortunately by Pakistan yes
so uh whether it's the 1948 uh War
whether it is a 1965 or the 1971 war or
the 1999 the Cargill War each of these
wars has been initiated by Pakistan
India has no desire India has never had
any desire to balkanize Pakistan or to
break up Pakistan it's only now that
India people in India are speaking about
this because we need to find a solution
once in our once and for all to the
problem that India has faced since 1947
right that's the only reason why people
in India are talking about balkanes in
Pakistan and it's something that could
happen you know so if Pakistan can get
its uh
act together
if Pakistan can overthrow the Army and
and establish a genuinely peaceful and
Democratic uh government
and and if Pakistan gives up it's uh
never-ending desire to break up and
Destroy India yeah then I'm sure we can
live together in peace obviously that's
High Hopes yeah so yeah anyway it's good
to see that people on Pakistan people in
on the Pakistani side also have this
desire for peace which actually tells us
that most people most likely on both
sides desire peace it's only certain
elements that have see Pakistan is
whether we like it or not it's an
artificially created Nation it's been
created it has been created by the the
British by the Western forces to further
their geopolitical interests it's an
artificial Nation that's been created
and artificial Nations unfortunately
don't tend to last very long in the big
picture of History if you see Nations
that have been created in this manner
they typically don't last a century or
two centuries you know so so that's the
problem that Pakistan faces it's in
unstable Nation it's a nation that's
cobbled together uh from uh through
outside interference it's a nation that
is is always on the on the brink of
disaster it's always being bailed out by
outside forces either by China or by by
the U.S yeah
so if Pakistan if the people of Pakistan
can somehow
get rid of the army we you do need an
army to safeguard your National interest
I'm not saying you don't have you should
not have an army I'm saying that the
Army should not run the country in every
country the nation has an Army in the
case of Pakistan the Army has a nation
it's the other way around
so the Army is a parasitic organism
that's that's preying on the people in
in the nation of Pakistan if Pakistan
can establish a genuine democracy in a
peaceful democracy then I don't see why
India and Pakistan cannot coexist
together yeah and in the in in such a
case if Pakistan becomes a genuinely
friendly and peaceful neighbor India
will be happy to lend a helping hand to
the Pakistan there have been so many
leaders who in India you know Prime
Ministers and so on who have wanted the
best of relations with Pakistan it's a
never-ending story in India so it's not
like there is no desire there's a lack
of Desire from India's side the problem
is it has always been been the Pakistani
army in the Pakistani politicians yeah
so uh
so yeah if think if the Pakistani people
can
get their country in order and establish
a genuine peaceful democracy then I'm
sure that India will be happy to coexist
peacefully and help Pakistan in any any
possible way and obviously India will
need the land access back yeah be the
land border with Afghanistan so let us
see how that goes but that's where we
are right now it's not exactly the ideal
situation yeah
that is where we are right now
okay let us take the next question
Daniel Nicholson says uh you explained
the Heartland theory which makes it
under easier to understand the role of
the US in Ukraine
uh how much do you think Russian
interests are at stake should Russia
fail to Prevail in the Ukraine special
military operation what would be
Russia's stance should an Indo China
Clash break out could see uh the
direction of the the US okay we are
talking about uh Russia the and and the
Ukraine military special military
operation so once again let's take a
look at the the map because that gives
us the right context so the special
military operation is clearly as we know
happening north of the Black Sea in the
Ukraine region yes uh so let's
understand what so you're saying what
what would happen if Russia were to fail
in this operation right so how do we
Define failure from the Russian
perspective and what are the various uh
uh forces that are at play over here so
the major forces are in this special
operation in Ukraine or Russia and NATO
NATO essentially means the United States
okay so what are Russia's objectives and
what are the American objectives we have
to understand that Russia has a certain
stated objective which is uh the
demilitarization and the denotcification
of Ukraine it obviously also wants to
reunify the donbas region with Russia
because it's a Russian majority region
the donbass region is the eastern and
southern part of Ukraine uh the kharkiv
lohansk Donetsk Mario Paul all those
regions right
so that is the non-negotiable part the
the the donbass region first of all
needs to be reunified with Russia yes uh
and the the other thing is that they
want to uh like they said uh D nazify
and demilitarize Ukraine what that
really means is they want to ensure that
Ukraine is no longer under U.S influence
because that is too close for comfort
for Russia yeah to have American
influence right at your doorstep from
the Russian perspective is a red line
that cannot allow be allowed to to be
crossed yeah so what the Russians
actually want is to eliminate all
American interference or influence from
Ukraine they obviously most likely want
a regime change in Kiev and maybe they
would allow the western part of Ukraine
to remain
you know to the rump state of Ukraine
and they would reunify the donbasa
region with Russia they would install a
puppet regime in cave and maybe the the
one-third western part of Ukraine could
be allowed to remain you cream that most
likely could be the long-term scenario
understand that this is not something
they want in 2022 or 2023 it's always a
long-term plan in geopolitics whatever
is happening now is in pursuance of a
long-term objective which is a 20 30 40
50 year objective that's always how it
is in geopolitics okay nobody does
anything which is a knee-jerk reaction
it's always I mean no good leader would
do that only uh
you know a bad leader doesn't need jerk
reactions whatever is happening here is
part of long-term objectives there are
long-term American objectives and there
are long-term Russian objectives so the
Russians want to eliminate all American
influence from the Ukraine region that
is number one right
what the what the Americans want they
want Ukraine to come fully under
American influence and in the long term
they would like Russia to be balkanized
and they would like to regain the access
to Russia that they had during the Boris
Yeltsin era so uh after uh the breakup
of the USSR uh Boris elsin became the
leader of Russia and he was in all ways
up in every single way a pro-western
leader he was one could say a western
stooge that's what the Russians think of
him they also think of Mikhail Gorbachev
in in much the same way so the Americans
would like to have that sort of access
once again within Russia eventually they
would like to uh possibly break up
Russia and gain access to the incredible
natural resources that the the that
Russia possesses this entire immense
territory that Russia straddles is home
to about half of the entire planet's
natural resources in terms of uh raw
materials
uh oil gas coal Metals uh iron iron ore
and much more you know agriculture so
much more so the Americans would love to
gain access to all that and they would
love to see somebody a weak leader come
to power in the Kremlin yes so that's
the kind of long-term objectives the
Americans have the Russians would like
to see what would the Russian what would
the Russian long-term objective be
Ukraine is not the long-term objective
the long-term objective is to recreate
the kind of
structure the the USSR had essentially
you could call it you know a few a few
months back I had this live stream which
in which I had uh I had given the title
of akhand Russia right so they would
like to recreate a USSR kind of
situation A Kanda Russia kind of thing
yeah they would like to recreate the
Warsaw Pact or or uh the Warsaw Pact
kind of satellite states that the USSR
had and they would like to regain some
territories that they've lost eventually
in the long run yes uh so that's the
kind of long-term objective Russia has
to recreate something like the USSR the
long-term objective of the US is to uh
regain influence that they had in Russia
to get rid of somebody like Putin and to
have a weak leader again in Russia and
oh hopefully to balkanize Russia and
gain access to all the natural resources
and everything else in Russia so these
are the two competing objectives so what
would it mean for Russia to fail it
means that they'll be unable to dislodge
America from Ukraine that is what it
means for Russia to fail in the Ukraine
special military operation right
so right now it's still in the balance
the Russians control about a quarter of
what used to be Ukraine and now the
winter is very much in yeah it's very
much enforced now the Rasputin is over
so there could be a Russian winter
offensive happening sometime that's what
everybody is expecting now so let's see
how that goes so if that fails if the
Russians are unable
to uh effect a regime change in Ukraine
that's what it means for them to fail if
that happens then Mr Putin's uh future
is in doubt because he will be seen to
have failed in in his attempt to uh to
regain Rustin Russian Prestige and
Russian influence in the region and then
things are things would go bad for him
so he cannot afford to fail if he fails
if he fails in in raised in in
dislodging Mr zielinski and appointing a
puppet president in in cave then in the
long run things could go bad for Russia
itself Mr Putin May perhaps fall out of
power maybe uh somebody else could come
in power it's all speculation but that's
how things could go yeah
so everything is at stake for Russia for
Russia it's essentially a fight for
survival yeah for Russia it's a fight
for survival for the for the Americans
it's uh they they are trying it they
would like to expand further so the
Americans are not fighting for survival
they are they are fighting for expansion
they are they have been relentlessly
expanding westwards NATO has been
relentlessly expanding Westward since
the 1990s uh you know they had given
assurances that they would not do that
but they have been doing it ever since
the 1999 it is so uh now Russia is is
trying to stop the expansion and if they
succeed then the Americans will have to
stop at that point and they will keep on
trying in other in other ways as well
so that's the situation for Russia it's
a struggle for survival if they succeed
then they will perhaps go into expansion
mode slowly yeah of course it will all
depend on who comes after Mr Putin if Mr
Putin succeeds in this operation then he
will obviously have to think about who
is going to be his successor in the long
run because uh he's obviously I think
we're across 70 70 years of age more or
less
so I don't see him lasting another 10
years that would be too much I mean
obviously in the U.S you have you have a
130 year old president right now that's
okay but typically people do not uh
stay on As Leaders at past a certain age
so for Russia it's a struggle for
survival for the for the Americans uh
it's a challenge to their expansionism
that's the situation yeah uh and what
would Russia's stance be to an
indo-china Clash which were supposedly
to break out well the Russian Russians
would want to be neutral yeah they will
officially adopt a neutral position they
will uh urge both sides to uh stop
fighting and go to the negotiating table
and find a peaceful Solution that's what
would be the official status
unofficially they would want India to
come out on dot because China is a big
threat to them yeah but yeah the
situation is complicated so that's what
I can say about this matter
now let's talk about this sino-soviet
split it's a question by rodrig sarkar
jit says you have told us about the 1969
sino-soviet Clash border Clash after the
sino-soviet split but why did the
sino-soviet split happen in the first
place both countries were important to
each other for many reasons
did the Americans have any role in this
okay so let's talk about The sino-soviet
Clash
um
the USSR in China both were communist
countries right we know that or in the
USSR you had the great strongman Joseph
Stalin in China you had the great
strongman Mao Zedong yeah so that's the
situation that you had in in the 1940s
and 1950s now uh Mao Zedong regarded
Stalin as as a great hero of his yeah he
had genuine respect for Joseph Stalin
yeah uh the USSR always treated China
uh
always treated China as a junior partner
China was a very poor Nation it was a
nation that was in shambles broken up
the USSR had had built up this enormous
Industries they had come out on top in
World War II they had a very strong
powerful army they had developed nuclear
weapons so they obviously were one of
the two big superpowers and they always
treated China as a junior partner and
Mao Sedum was fine with that as long as
Joseph started was in power in the USSR
because he had genuine admiration and
respect for Joseph Stalin
now Joseph Stalin died in 1953 yes Mao
Zedong lived on for a long much longer
time so Joseph Stalin dies in 1953 and
in his place comes a new leader Nikita
Khrushchev who wasn't power for about
nine years 1953 to 1964 or something so
that's Nikita Khrushchev now
Mao Zedong did not respect
Nikita Khrushchev do any
in any way the the way that he respected
Joseph silent he did not have any kind
any of that kind of respect for Nikita
Khrushchev he found Nikita to be
ideologically
vacillating ideologically weak and not
uh worthy of the kind of respect that
Joseph Stalin deserved yeah
um
so uh Nikita Christian was in power
until from 1953 to 1964 from 1964 to
about 1981 82 you had Leonid the
Brezhnev who was in Joseph in Mao
tutong's eyes an even weaker leader and
all of these things they eventually led
to the Sino Soviet split so while Stalin
was in power
uh Martha dung was okay with the Soviets
treating China as a junior partner but
when these leaders who came and came in
after Stalin who Mao did not respect
that much and who he considered to be
kind of weak and ideologically
questionable and then the USSR still
continues treating China as a junior
partner that kind of rankled with uh Mao
setung and then there were these
ideological uh clashes so on the one
hand you had the ussr's Marxism leninism
on the other hand you had China's maoism
so the maoists Mao believed that uh see
in in Marxism in communism in Marxism
especially you have the idea of the
people's Revolution right this Society
is a revolutionary Society these are the
dictatorship of the proletariat and all
that so Mao believed that a
revolutionary Society should be led by
the peasantry The Peasants the farmers
you know the proletariat
he believed that the Soviet Union's
model of of socialism of Communism was
too centralized it was too bureaucratic
and was kind of Bourgeois it was not
revolutionary enough yeah and this this
uh perception became accentuated after
the demise of Joseph Joseph and the uh
coming to power of Nikita Khrushchev and
later yes
uh Mao also did not like the Soviet
Union's uh policy of of uh what he
considered to be peaceful coexistence
with the uh capitalist Nations like the
US the Soviets wanted to somehow coexist
with the capitalist Nations like the US
and the Soviets wanted to show
eventually that we will come out on top
and our our system our ideology is the
best
but Mao did not like it he did not like
that the Soviets wanted to coexist
peacefully with the capitalist countries
he wanted to see a more vigorous and
robust struggle against the capitalist
countries and the capitalist ideology
and he also was displeased with the
Soviet Union's lack of support for
various revolutionary movements around
the world the Soviets did support
various revolutionary movements and so
on but that was for geopolitical
purposes not from ideological reasons
yeah so Mao was from that perspective a
little more ideological and a little
more um idealistic you could say and the
other thing is that the USSR was
focusing on Eastern Europe it wanted to
increase its influence in Eastern Europe
in what what we just spoke about the
Warsaw Pact countries these uh the
Eastern Europe uh satellite states of
the USSR yeah and the USSR was focusing
on countering the U.S in that region
whereas China was focusing on Console
editing its control over China and
spreading communism again in Revolution
in the third world so it was again more
ideological
from the Chinese perspective so you had
these very Stark differences mainly
ideological differences so uh from the
maoist perspective from the Chinese
perspective the Soviets were going soft
and they were not communist enough and
they were not a hard line enough yeah
and obviously we had the personal
animosity between Mao Zedong and Nikita
Khrushchev so that also was a factor so
all of this eventually uh led to what we
call the cyanosovic's bit which is
slowly happened after the death of
Stalin from the 1950s to the 1960s
onwards you had which all culminated in
the disaster of the usuri river clashes
of 1969 let's go to the map where's the
map here's the map where's the map here
we are the usury River clashes which the
usury river is now the Border of uh of
the of Russia and China so somewhere
over here we had this island what was it
called the genbao island
where's
okay I always I try to find it and then
I miss it I'm sure it's here somewhere
is it here
let's just uh Google it for convenience
gen Bao Island
is here it's here the island is here so
it's over here that the uh this became a
flash point the two Nations
clashed over here there were rather
brutal military clashes several hundred
soldiers died total both sides claimed
that the other side they lost more
soldiers and all that in the aftermath
of the osuri river clashes
uh the USSR actually decided
to Nuke China yeah the Soviets decided
to Nuke China and it was the Americans
that intervened the Americans intervened
and they threatened Russia with a
retaliatory strike they threatened the
USSR that the Retaliator is like if the
Soviets went ahead with a nuclear strike
on China essentially it's the Americans
that saved China and this action
eventually paved the way for the
sino-american they thought which
happened under the leadership of
who was it Nixon Nixon Kissinger and Mao
Zedong and that's what happened right so
that is the whole deal so the Sino
Soviet split was mainly ideological and
also we had differences of perception of
the Border in various other factors and
animosity between the leaders of the two
Nations all of these things combined
together to create this sino-soviet spit
that's how it happened all right
right
once again
we know that Russia gradually moved to
the East and annexed a huge chunk of
land but what happened to the native
people of those conquered lands good
question I have not heard anyone asked
this thus far what happened to the
native people of those conquered lands
did they suffer the same fate as the
Native Americans this is a very good
question and rather important
it's a rather important question what
happened to those conquered people of in
those conquered lands did they suffer
the same fate as the Native Americans
let's once again go
back
to the map or give me a second
we need to take a look at the map to
understand how things are how things
went
so let's go back to the 13th century
yeah let's go back to the 13th century
uh in the 13th century first half of the
13th century
you had the great Mongol conqueror
the great warrior for peace Shri chingis
Khan who had conquered an enormous
territory in an incredibly short amount
of time he conquered more territory in
20 years than the then the Roman Empire
was able to conquer in two and a half
centuries yeah uh so that's what Genghis
Khan did and during Genghis Khan's
lifetime two of his generals who are the
JBE in subotai or somebody else I forget
the name two of his generals they went
on an expedition a reconnaissance
expedition in the west all right
um after the conquest of quarasma
um it's a whole in very interesting
story it it it ends up on the borders of
India which I have covered in a
different video on the channel so in the
aftermath of the Mongol conquest of
juarasma two of his generals went on a
reconnaissance mission and they
encountered Russians for the first time
after the death of Sri Genghis Khan his
son Khan became the Khan and later the
Mongol Empire expanded much further and
the Slavic peoples and the Russians fell
under what they call the Mongol Yoke the
Mongols conquered Russia
so this happened in the 13th century and
until the late 15th century the Russians
were under the Mongol yoke they were
conquered people and and they they were
ruled by the Mongols it's by the 1480s
or so that the Russians were able to
throw off the Mongol occupation that's
when he had the great principality of
moscovy that became a genuine power and
then
the from the 16th century onwards the
Russians started expanding eastwards now
what was the reason for this expansion
eastwards it was all for the fur trade
fur was a very valuable commodity and
these enormous lands this enormous
expansion expanse of lands in in eastern
in in Northern Eurasia was had plentiful
resources of first you know various
animals that that have these winter
coats you know that that were the they
would be hunted and their skins would be
taken and used for far and this was a
very lucrative trade and the Russians
wanted to capitalize on that so they
started expanding eastwards gradually
and They Came Upon all these various
peoples you know turkic peoples and
other peoples whom they slowly gradually
conquered so this was a process that
started in the 16th century and it
culminated in the
eventual uh conquest of the entirety of
what is now Eastern Russia in the 19th
century and they even took over Parts of
Alaska in the 19th century now the
entirety of Alaska in the 19th century
uh by the mid 19th century they had
taken over all of Alaska it was
eventually sold to the U.S because the
Russians believed that there was not
much of value over there it was it was
you know too far away
uh so um
so all of this territory was conquered
over a period of about 300 or so years
and they conquered all the peoples who
lived here you have all these different
you know ethnicities Olivia turkic
peoples uh the the I knew people in in
the Far East you know uh in the sakhalin
region in in north of Hokkaido in the
kurul islands uh
the Kamchatka Peninsula all that you
have the I know I know people I knew
people the kamchatkan people the people
the tongue people in the tungus uh
region uh various turkic uh ethnicities
the altai peoples the tatars home with
whom the the Russians had significant
amount of strife now the tatars are one
of the major ethnic groups in Russia you
have the yakutian peoples the mongolic
peoples north of who lived north of
Mongolia the samoyedes the Aleutian
people so many more so many more peoples
were conquered and and they were so what
happened to them is the question
did they suffer the same fate as the
Native Americans the question then
obviously which which begs itself is
what happened to the Native Americans
was a systematic genocide at least 56
million Native Americans were wiped out
in just about a century or so I have
showed you the references in the past in
in the past video I'm not going to dig
it out once again you can look it up
it's it's well known yeah and over a
period of about
three or so centuries at least a hundred
million Native Americans would have lost
their lives because of the European
occupation of their territories so when
it comes to the Native Americans it was
deliberate systematic genocide these
people were wiped out of existence
that's what happened to the Native
Americans and that's how North America
is now all you know settled by European
origin people and the natives are not
even seconded but the third-rate
citizens in these lands in their own
ancestral lands what happened to the
native people of of Siberia in North
Eurasia was not quite what happened to
the Native Americans yes they were
defeated yes they were conquered there
would have been massacres there would
have been atrocities but it wasn't it
would it it did not culminate in what
you could consider to be genocide what
happened was you could call cultural
assimilation or cultural imposition
cultural imperialism
um to some extent yeah so all these
peoples were forcibly ratified they were
made to start they were made to speak
Russian uh many of them possibly were
converted to Christian Catholicism or
Orthodox Russian Christianity and there
was some reverse
rivers in culturation as well
Buddhism entered the Russian life you
know the Russian cultural sphere a
significant popular percentage of
Russia's population today is Buddhist
principally uh it's uh it's principally
Tibetan Buddhism that you have in Russia
and that initially came in through the
Mongols because the Mongols practiced
the Tibetan Buddhism we've spoken about
this in the past on this channel
up
so all of these peoples today who live
in Russia whether it is north of
Mongolia whether it is the altai altai
people the two one people the yakut
people the illusion people the mongolic
peoples the Samoyeds the tongosik
peoples whoever it is they all more or
less speak Russian as one of their
principal languages if not the principal
language then the second language but
they are all perfectly fluent in Russian
as if it's the native language yeah uh
so all of these people were ratified it
was a process of rustification
it was not exactly genocide it was
nothing close to what happened to the
Native American peoples but yes these
people these people their territories
became Russian territories and they lost
whatever control they had so they were
made to become Russian citizens and they
had to obey the Russian laws and all
that stuff yeah
and eventually all of this became part
of Russia so it was all Conquest but it
was not genocide it was a russification
of all these regions so that is
essentially what happened they did not
say for the suffer the same fate is the
Native Americans but the territories
were taken and they lost control of they
lost sovereignty over these territories
that's essentially what happened
Shaheen
zadigan says what was the 4.2 kilo year
event and was this a crucial factor in
the end of the Saraswati Sindhu era in
India all right that's a great question
so in the past you may remember I have
spoken about uh
an ancient geopolitical event between
India and the Acadian Empire
that was in the 43rd Century BC
sorry that was in the 23rd Century BC uh
it was
in in the year 2200 something BC or so
there was this king called Remus of
akkad he was a second king of the
akkadian Empire he was the son of the
great Sargon of akad he ruled for less
than a decade but he went to war with
the people of ilam and with the people
of marhashi and
and the people of ilam and marashi they
had allies in India in India at the time
was what we call the so-called Indus
Valley Civilization civilization and it
is recorded in The Arcadian Chronicles
that the Indians send sent soldiers to
the aid of maharashi and and uh ilam and
apparently the the acadians won that the
conflict
so India participated in a war outside
of what was traditionally called India
in what is now Persia or Iran yeah and
it was with the Acadian Empire which was
based in what is now Iraq
so this event happened
in
the 2200s BC between 22 around 20 to 75
20 to 78 or something BC that's when it
happened
about a century after that
we have the 4.2 kilo year event
a century or so after this after this
war yeah after rebush of akad
so this 4.2 kilo year event happened in
the 22nd century BC in the 23rd Century
BC we had this war with remote
so this 4.2 kilo year event was about a
century it lasted about a century or so
it was a century of drought
approximately 100 Years of very less
rainfall and significant drought
worldwide globally
in India in China in the Middle East in
Africa drought drought drought
everywhere yeah so around this time we
know that the great Saraswati river
which was a rain-fed river which
originated in the Himalayas and went all
the way into the sea of saurashtra which
is now called a spuriously the Arabian
Sea this River was already declining
the Indian Monsoon started declining
monotonically around 6000 BC slow
decline of the Indian Monsoon because of
this the Saraswati River started
declining too slowly and gradually
and in because of this 4.2 kilo year
event this decline was significantly
precipitated and it's probably around
this time the river stopped reaching the
sea and it ended in this big lake which
eventually dried out and it is now
called the far desert the third desert
let's go once once again back to the map
so if you go to India to Western India
we have the great Thar Desert you see
the entire region of Rajasthan yeah it's
all it's all brownish yellowish over
here yeah that is the enormous Thar
Desert most likely the Saraswati River
dried out and and stopped reaching the
sea and it ended up in a big lake or
puddle or Marsh in this region which
eventually dried out and gave raised to
rise to all the sand dunes the kind of
thing that you see in the Aral Sea today
the same sort of thing yeah when a big
lake or sea dries out what you get is a
desert with sand dunes and all that
so most likely as a result of the 4.2
kilo year event this the rivers stopped
reaching the sea
um and yes this most likely was a
crucial factor in the end of the
Saraswati Sindhu era in Western India so
Western India thisindu region which is
the region of the Sindhu River the great
Indus River uh the Saraswati which no
longer exists mostly and the various
other rivers in this region this was a
very fertile region and that's where you
had the main uh
focus of the civilization of that time
our civilization of that time
which historians call the Indus Valley
Civilization
so around this time because of the
drying out of the Saraswati and very
less Monsoon and all that there were
significant migrations out of the region
and these migrations most likely started
around this time around the 4.2 kilo
year event
and people were forced to migrate to
other parts of the region many of them
went eastwards many of them went
northwards northwards you still had lots
of water many rivers India obviously is
a river valley civilization
so many more
so people were made were forced to give
up the lifestyle they had been living
for several thousand years and they were
forced to migrate to other parts of
India but the migrations were not only
eastwards into what we now call Mainland
India many of these migrations were also
West words yeah
and it's around this time that you have
the uh that that you have the infamous
Rampage of the so-called yamne amen
across Europe right and it's around this
time also that you have various other
things happening which indicate a Indian
presence far west of India so yes
the 4.2 kilo year event was a major
period of drought approximately it
lasted approximately A Century of
drought you know and yes it was
definitely a crucial factor in a
complete reconfigure reconfiguration of
society and life in the Indian
subcontinent and in various other parts
of the world and it could be what
precipitated the slow the the gradual
decline of what we call the Saraswati
Hindu civilization that's that phase of
Indian civilization or the Harappan
phase of the Indus Valley phase yeah so
slowly these cities had to be they were
slowly abandoned and people moved
elsewhere and eventually the cities fell
out of use and they they are the way
they we see them now so that was the 4.2
kilo year event it was a major drought
and it kind of reconfigured Life all
across the planet yep
AB says you told us about zebu cattle
migration z-e-bu zebu is it possible
that the yamaya people Invasion or
migration is connected to the zebu
cattle migration a good question yeah so
once again let's go here
so I spoke about the zebu Capital
migration what are the zebu cattle let's
first of all take a look at what a zebu
cattle looks like uh let us go back to
where are we let's do Google search for
zebu cattle shall we
cartel what does Zebo cattle look like
a standard Indian cattle the bulls with
the big humps on their shoulders this is
what you see in the Ashoka inscriptions
and pillars and all that these are the
the seals that you see in the Saraswati
Sindhu region yeah
Indus Valley seals with the humped bulls
with this big dewlap you know under the
chin this big fold of skin and all this
is the zebu cattle these are the zebu
Kettle these are the standard Indian
cattle Indian origin cattle and it is
known genetically and scientifically
these cattle originate in India these
are Indian cattle they have come from
nowhere else right
so what do we find
what do we know about the zebu Kettle I
have spoken about the zebu cattle
migration what we find let's now go to
the map let's now go to the map and let
me tell you what happened
so once again where is the map here is
the map let's take a look at it
here
so about
about 4 200 years ago which kind of
coincides with this uh 4.2 kilo year
event
around this time
it is known that all of a sudden zebu
Bulls
started breeding with boss Taurus female
cattle right across the Fertile Crescent
which is this region Iraq the Eastern
Mediterranean region Anatolia Egypt all
of this all of this is called the
Fertile Crescent
around 4.2 000 years ago Indian zebu
Bulls started breeding with female
boss Taurus
cattle in this region the Fertile
Crescent region now Bulls a cattle they
don't migrate on their own it's not like
a bunch of cattle say hey let's go for a
walk and they go all the way to Egypt it
doesn't happen like that cattle only
migrate with humans cattle are
domesticated species they have been
domesticated for thousands of years in
India so if cattle suddenly started
breeding with local uh if Indian booths
are certainly started certainly appear
in the Fertile Crescent and start
breeding with the local female cattle
over there it means Indian people
migrated to this region and brought
these bulls with them yeah
and we have archaeological evidence in
Egypt from approximately 2000 BC of zebu
cattle including uh depictions of zebu
cattle on on pottery and rocks and other
such inscriptions and all that yeah
so
so that's what happened approximately
4.2 000 years ago and like I said after
the 4.2 kilo year event people
were in in the Indian subcontinent were
forced to migrate in different
directions many of them went eastwards
and many of them actually went westwards
and that coincides with the arrival of
these cattle these Bulls Indian Bulls in
the Fertile Crescent region yeah
migrations can happen very fast you see
the the what is now Pakistan and Iran
the border is is very much dry it's very
easy to cross so you can cross this
region on foot in a matter of months in
a matter of weeks actually yeah even if
you have a large herd of cattle with you
it's not difficult to cross this region
obviously you will eventually run into
the Zagros Mountains and all that but
it's not very difficult to cross this
region
so very rapidly after the 4.2 year kilo
year event you have Indians arriving in
this region you have the arrival of zebu
cattle in Egypt itself yeah and this is
just a few centuries before the arrival
before the the Empire of the Hittites
the Empire of the mittani and the the
invasion of the hexas people into Egypt
this is this all seems to be a set of
coincidences that all happen at the same
time this cannot be coincidences this is
all interconnected history is not a set
of coincidences history is a set of of
uh cause and effect events it's all
causality it's all interconnected yeah
so what happens
is that people seem to have migrated
from the Saraswati Sindhu Valley region
into Central Asia into the Middle East
into Africa Etc approximately 4 200
years ago which coincides with the 4.2
kilo year event and these people most
likely introduced zebu cattle ancestry
into these regions today you have zebu
cattle and you have cattle all across
Africa that have zebu cattle ancestry
all across Africa even in central Africa
even in Eastern Africa today yeah
when these ebook cattle are
unambiguously unmistakably of Indian
origin and you have Zebo cattle ancestry
even in Europe and all that so that's a
whole different story so that is the
deal now the question is about the
yamnea invasion also so The yamne
Invasion happens is said to have
happened around
4500 years ago which kind of predates
by a few centuries the 4.2 kilo year
event and the introgression of Indian
cattle into the Middle East and Africa
so most likely the yamnya invasion of
Europe was a different event possibly
not connected to the 4.2 kilo year event
most likely the yamnya were people who
went out of India a few centuries before
the invasion of Europe
they most likely settled down in the
centralization step region for a few
centuries and then eventually for some
reason they decided to Rampage across
Europe and do the things that they did
yeah
so most likely and we know that the
yamanea were horse riding
Invaders they were Fierce Warriors they
they swept aside everything that came in
front of them nobody could uh withstand
The yamanea Invasion yeah and they were
definitely not cattle Farmers these were
warriors these were horse riders they
were not Nomads would would move slowly
from one place to another their rampaged
across Europe at an unimaginable speed
so most likely the yamnya people are not
connected with the zebu cattle they
definitely seem to be of Indian origin
yeah uh and the r1b haplogroup is what
you find predominantly predominantly
among these men the yamnaya were mostly
men mostly men very few women uh and and
all that yeah
so that's the deal so the zebu cattle
migration seems to be a completely dis
unconnected event from the uh yamnea
Invasion The Invasion predates the
arrival of zebu cattle in
in uh the Fertile Crescent by about
three or four centuries yeah so most
likely these are even that are not
connected to each other
says what was the basis for the
hypothesis of chronology of different
metal ages like the Bronze Age Iron Age
Etc
uh as the indologists put the timeline
of Rick Veda much earlier because of the
mentioning of iron in the text even
neglecting other factors
evolution of language and from rig
weather and all kinds of things okay the
question is about the chronology of
metal ages so we have what is called the
so-called three age system the Stone Age
the Bronze Age and the Iron Age right so
so where does this originate so there
was a guy
it all starts with a guy what was the
name guy's name his name he was a Danish
archaeologist let's let's Google the guy
yeah let's go to Google
where is Google here we are let us
Google Christian
Jurgensen
Tom
this is the name of the guy he was a
Danish
antiquarian archaeologist whatever yeah
and in the early 19th century he
developed what is called the three age
system the three-age system proposed
that the chronology of human history
it went through three different ages
first you had the Stone Age then you had
the Bronze Age and then you had the Iron
Age so and in each age was more
sophisticated than the previous age so
in the Stone Age humans could only use
stone tools yeah they were very
primitive backward people our ancestors
they did not have any any knowledge of
of
of uh metal metals and all that yeah so
that was a stone age which went on for a
very long time then you had the Bronze
Age so humans are acquired the ability
to to to uh to create bronze tools tools
and weapons so you have bronze swords
bronze uh vessels and things like that
and eventually there was an Iron Age
which was more sophisticated which was
which required better technology more
sophisticated technology advanced
technology than during the Bronze Age so
that is the hypothesis that this person
made in the early 19th century and ever
since then we have been following this
and there obviously has been criticism
of this that you know it's a very simple
oversimplification it's a very over
simplistic model of the progress of of
human history and human evolution and
all that it's not always like this and
like saurabh says in the rig Veda there
there is mention of iron
uh so then
there is mention of ayas right ayas is
well is it iron or is it some other
metal we're not quite sure but most
likely it means iron
so if people were using iron our
ancestors were using iron during the rig
Vedic Age well that pushes back the Iron
Age to a whole uh to a time period way
before what is uh conventionally
understood to be the Iron Age
and then we have to ask others of the
question as to when was the rigveda
written now if you ask romila thapar she
will say it was written after 1500 BC It
Was Written maybe 3000 years ago that's
what the Indian Marxist historians will
tell you which is all nonsense from a
variety of logical reasons yeah the rig
with obviously mentions that Saraswati
is a great River we know what happened
to the Saraswati around 4 200 years ago
she started drying out very badly yeah
so clearly this is written and this also
they started declining around 6000 BC
with the with the beginning of the
decline of the Indian Monsoon so the
regular is clearly written at a time
closer to 6000 BC then to 1500 BC yeah
the second thing is that the rigveda
clearly describes the Society of the
time it describes a rural pastoral
Society
it describes a pre-saraspati Sindhu
civilization Society
the Saraswati Hindu phase of our history
of our civilization was a magnificently
urbanized phase of History
our civilization was entirely Urban
extremely technologically advanced and a
very large population for that time yeah
in a huge population area a huge
geographical area
the rig the society that is described in
the texts or in the text of the rig Veda
is not an urban Society it's not a very
technologically advanced Society
yeah in the in the case of monumental
architecture and Roads and grid system
and in multi-stored buildings and and
Hydro Engineering and all that the Rigby
that doesn't describe any of that
the rigveda describes a rural pastoral
Society
yeah so this is clearly something that
today's historians would describe as
pre-harappan
yeah the pre-harapan phase is way before
four four thousand is it's way before
4000 BC
so once again
seems to have been written closer to
6000 BC than than to three thousand or
four thousand BC so clearly the rig
weather is way older than what these
people have been claiming it is
and then the rigveda we know it has
references to IAS which is iron most
likely
so if the Indian Iron Age was about 6000
BC that kind of
messes up the chronology that uh that
our friend what's his name Christian
Jurgensen Thompson came up with yeah
so this entire hypothesis of the
chronology of of the this three-age
system the Stone Age the Bronze Age the
Iron Age it is not a hard and fast rule
it's something that somebody came up
with just like somebody came up with the
Aryan Invasion Theory it's not you know
when someone comes up with a theory it
has to stand the test of time and it has
to match the observational evidence and
clearly the iron Invasion Theory doesn't
match that and maybe in the case of
um the three uh age system maybe there
also doesn't match what we know about uh
about our history so that is the thing
so the basis is just a hypothesis the
basis for the three age system the
chronology of the mental ages is just a
hypothesis that or a theory that uh a
Danish uh archaeologist came up with
it's not something we have to uh worship
as something that said in stone just
like the Indian constitution yeah it's
it's a hypothesis that somebody came up
with and
it it's not something that is a set in
stone or iron or bronze
all right
Daniel Nicholson says if the temporary
State Pakistan engages India on our
Western theater as the people Republic
People's Republic of China's really
lieutenant
which would engage India the North and
Northeast we would only have to use the
nuclear option to decide Pakistan's fate
within the first five minutes in this
case wouldn't the U.S directly get a
premise to premise to send its invasive
Fleet to Indian Shores what would be the
end result of this chaotic War garbhit
Singh Johan says with the USA constantly
supporting Pakistan and Russia not
compromising you know three relations
with China will India be able to
independently sustain a two-front war
let me answer garvey's question first
it is likely that if India goes to war
with China it will also simultaneously
be engaged in the war with Pakistan if
India and China go to war the pakistanis
will most likely also attack we have to
be prepared for that and so
the solution in case of a two-front war
is to extinguish one front as soon as
possible
now Pakistan is no match for India in
terms of military might
so the the thing the solution if if
India is embroiled in a two-front war is
to extinguish one war immediately as
soon as possible and that's why I said
in the past that in case Pakistan
initiates a war with India in the future
that war should be the last war India
fights with Pakistan
and the outcome of that war should be
decided in the first five minutes that's
what I had said now Daniel seems to have
interpreted that as as meaning a nuclear
strike
my friends I will never ever Advocate a
nuclear strike
the nuclear option is something nobody
should ever use
all right
so when I said that the outcome of the
war should be decided in the first five
minutes I did not mean a nuclear strike
I meant a conventional missile strike
a massive missile strike
a preemptive strike to end all strikes
that's what I meant I do not mean a
nuclear strike we should never ever use
the nuclear option now the question is
if India wipes out Pakistan in the first
five minutes will it not give the U.S a
premise to send an invasion Fleet to
India
if Pakistan initiates the war India has
the right to retaliate and respond
India as a sovereign nation has the
right
to go to war if provoked
in which case nobody has the right
or nobody has the will have any
pretext
to send an invasion Fleet to India yeah
and what's the point of sending an
invasion Fleet by the time the
pakistanis will be dealt with yeah and
we'll be dealing with China
so uh so the thing is India should not
initiate the next war with Pakistan
but if Pakistan initiates the next War
it should be the final war and the
outcome should be decided in the first
five minutes
not through a nuclear strike but through
conventional means and if it should take
out the ability of Pakistan to launch a
strike a nuclear strike on India yeah
so I mean I am just giving
you know a big picture thing obviously
the Indian armed forces in the
government know better how to go about
doing things but what's clear is that
the outcome has to be decided very
rapidly very very rapidly it should not
be a war that is drawn out and it gets
into tank warfare and long long donut
tactics and all it should be
decided instantly within the first five
minutes
by taking out Pakistan's ability to
inflict any kind of damage on India
immediately take out all their airfields
take out all the all their aircraft take
out all the radars and take out their
nuclear facilities or whatever else
whatever
sensitive and critical installations and
all that they have those need to be
taken out immediately which is why I
always keep saying India needs massive
stockpiles of missiles 50 missiles 100
missiles 200 missiles will not do the
trick India needs a stockpile of at
least 10 000 missiles of different kinds
that's what a major world power does
yeah
so that is the deal
in case of a two front War the the one
front needs to be extinguished
immediately you can't let two fronts uh
simmer on for a long time so the
Pakistani problem has to be dealt with
instantly once and for all that problem
should be finished
the next time the pakistanis instigator
initiative war with India we should not
initiate the war we are we
you have never initiated a war with
Pakistan or with China yes we have
always responded in the future also if
the pakistanis start a war if they do we
should end it very quickly and then deal
with the Chinese
this is all hypotheticals obviously
because uh India is not the kind of
nation that even the Chinese can afford
to really tangle with because they also
could end up um
suffering the kind of damage that would
not be nice for them so just a reminder
to our good Chinese friends
uh yeah so that's I think that's the
question and that I think I have
answered it yeah
so yeah the chaotic what there'll be no
chaotic War it'll be uh on off what
that's it with Pakistan with the Chinese
we'll deal with it separately
okay samrat says is India researching
about making nukes with thorium thorium
what impact will it have if India
obtains the technology of making nukes
with thorium Daniel says how practical
is the use usage of thorium as a means
of clean energy India accounts for a
quarter of the global thorium reserves
is it a practical solution to India's
power energy needs in the future how far
are we from harnessing thorium-based
electricity or thorium based nukes let's
see what thorium looks like let's Google
it it's a metal thorium is a metal
thorium-232.
two
sorry
um
it's a metallic element yeah that's what
it looks like thorium
232 that's what it is so thorium is not
a fissile material like uranium is yeah
it can't be used to create nuclear
weapons directly thorium can be
converted into
uranium-233 U2 to 233 which is a fissile
element and can be used in nuclear
weapons yep so uranium-233 is produced
by irradiating
thorium-232 with neutrons inside a
machine called a reactor a nuclear
reactor it's not your regular nuclear
reactor it needs a special kind of
nuclear reaction called a breeder
reactor so this process of creating
uranium-233 out of sodium-232 is not
simple it re it requires a special kind
of reactor called a breeder reactor a
breeder reactor is a special kind of
nuclear reactor which is capable of
producing more fissile material then
what it consumes yeah so you can have a
thorium-based nuclear reactor which is
different from uranium-based nuclear
reactors so it uses thorium
is the fuel source and it breeds new
fuel from thorium so that's what it does
So currently what we have is that there
are no commercial
thorium-based nuclear reactors in the
world we have various experimental
reactors that are being worked on in the
world many countries have various
development programs India has one of
the most advanced thorium research
programs in the world yeah India
obviously has a quarter of the entire
world's thorium resources yeah so India
is doing that we have the largest
thorium reserves in the world and we are
actively uh researching thorium-based
nuclear technology uh India has been
doing this for several decades I'm not
exactly sure where we are at yeah I
think the government of India has stated
that by 2050 about a third of our
electricity should come from
thorium-based reactors
so that's about 30 years in the future
by that time if you can perfect you know
or or if we can uh not perfect but
improve uh the reactor design and all
that then we could start uh building
thorium-based reactors so that's what we
could do so there is a great amount of
potential in thorium based nuclear
energy uh and the reactors can be
smaller as well and more efficient and
they will produce less of the harmful
radioactive waste that uh your typical
normal standard reactors produce and the
the chances of a nuclear meltdown also
are low because the temperatures in a
thorium-based reactor are also also also
lower so it's a win-win kind of
situation I'm not sure why all the
nations in the world like the US India
China France Etc have not gone fully
into thorium-based nuclear uh
power but it's certainly something that
needs that needs to happen now the other
question is what about uh making nukes
with thorium so yes you can use a
thorium reactor thorium-based nuclear
reactor to breed of reactor to produce
uranium-233 and technically you can
definitely produce a fissile material
that can be used in nuclear weapons in a
thorium reactor but you know the best
way to acquire uranium-235 which goes
into nuclear weapons is to use the
naturally occurring unit uranium over
which is mostly redm 238 and to uh
enrich that in centrifuges so this is a
much more efficient process it could it
can consumes
less resources less money
and it produces much more uh nuclear
fuel
weapons grade nuclear uh fuel then then
a thorium-based reactor would produce so
so uh
making nukes whether from a thorium
reactor is not the ideal way of doing it
ideally you you just do it by acquiring
uranium ore which is mostly 238 uranium
238 and then purifying it yeah enriching
it to weapons grid uranium which is 90
or more uranium-235 that's how we do it
that's a much more cost efficient and
overall efficient process using
centrifuge and all that so India does
that obviously I'm yeah that's how it is
but I think India should really focus on
the thorium nuclear uh Power
option I believe that India has one of
the most advanced thorium research
programs in the world uh and and the
stated objective of the government is to
generate at least 30 percent of India's
electricity from thorium-based reactors
by 2050. so let's go for it we we are
fortunate to have so so much uh such an
abundance of Thorium in India when it
comes to the monazite sands on the
eastern coast of India and the
reserves so we should use this and uh
and diversify our energy supplies I mean
this is obviously clean energy it's
green energy it doesn't have a carbon
footprint or anything so it's it's a
it's something that India really needs
to focus on
and that could really help India in the
long run
so that is the deal uh how far are we
from harnessing thorium-based
electricity or thorium-based nukes or
not so thorium-based nukes are mainly
mostly out of the question it doesn't
make sense to have thorium-based nukes
thorium is not a facile material you
have to create
uh so uranium-235 is the way to go when
it comes to nuclear weapons electricity
I'm not sure how far we are we have one
of the most advanced programs but I
don't know where exactly they are
hopefully by 2050 will be producing at
least a third of our electricity from
thorium-based reactors and that's uh and
that would be great
okay Daniel says Ah I think two or three
people asked most of the questions
most of the interesting questions
okay Daniel says when a thermonuclear
device or any nuclear device is
detonated is it possible to exactly
determine the impact diameter is that
diameter dependent on external factors
as well of course you can uh determine
the the radius
like you said the impact diameter so
when you detonate a nuclear weapon you
know what is the blast radius and what
is the radius uh in which everybody will
die everything will be flattened and the
radius at which a certain amount of
radiation goes out and all that it can
be calculated it's very simple yeah
it's mainly dependent on the yield of
the nuclear weapon the yield is
typically measured in in terms of
kilotons of TNT or megatons of TNT yeah
um I think the the largest weapon that
India has tested was a 60 kiloton
uh thermonuclear weapon yeah
and uh the Americans have a standard 100
kiloton weapon called The W something
and they have tested Megaton weapons as
well the Russians have tested the
largest weapon ever which was a 50
Megaton weapon which was called the Tsar
Bomba and all that yeah so uh yeah it's
it's pretty straightforward for a
nuclear physicist to calculate the the
blast radius and all that and there are
websites that can help you do that you
know so let's take a look at my websites
it's called Uh
it's called nuclear secrecy.com
something let's take a look at that nuke
map
just give me a second nuclear
secrecy.com slash nuke map let's put
that on the screen once again give me a
second and here we are
nuclear secrecy.com and and
this comes with all these preset options
you can so you can select any City
or you can select nuclear uh historical
locations
and it's it's uh it's pre-selected New
York City for some reason so uh
so I I hope nobody gets offended I'm not
uh so let's what do we see
okay just for the sake of taking a look
at this yeah let's let's do it on New
York City uh what yield do we want let's
take
a standard bomb
which is the largest Indian weapon 60
kilotons let's take the w76 which is
common in the US and UK slbm Arsenal
so we have a hundred kiloton nuclear
device the w76 we are focusing on New
York City which is what the website gave
me okay it's not my choice
and um
and we're gonna do US Air burst instead
of surface
or we could do a surface thing let's do
an Airbus which is like the bomb will
detonate in the air itself not on the
surface but not upon impact and let's
detonate boom
so there you go
so the fireball radius is 380 meters
that's the radius the radiation radius
is 5 is 1.11 kilometers the moderate
blast damage radius is 3.26 kilometers
and all that so it tells you what kind
of blast rate is it's going to have and
although it's standard calculations you
could uh use a North Korean weapon yeah
and then see what happens it's a
slightly larger one slightly larger
blast impact let's go for a one Megaton
bomb and see what happens it's a much
bigger radius
uh do they have sarbama
50 Megaton let's see boom enormous yeah
so that's how it is it's possible to
more or less exactly determine the
impact diameter you can also take a look
at the radioactive fallout which will
depend on the wind and all that so here
you have uh you can see the yellow
portion which is the radioactive fallout
which is dependent on the wind direction
so if the wind is uh in the direction of
the Northeast then it will go all the
way to Massachusetts and all that from
there
and yeah let's not take a look at
casualties which will depend on various
factors and all that so that's how it is
yep so uh this uh website is called
nuclear secrecy.com nuke map you can go
and take a look at it and play around
with the various settings and yeah
that's how it is yeah so it's definitely
possible to determine all these
parameters uh quite precisely depending
on the on the uh yield of the nuclear
weapon and the height at which you
donated and various other factors yeah
yeah hardik says Namaste yes you have
said multiple times that India needs to
rewrite its entire history and now the
home minister SRI amitsha made a few
comments recently okay uh so the
question is hypothetically if you are in
charge of this project of this plan how
would you approach this problem and how
do you fix the puzzle since the ASI is
useless and so many anti-indians resist
this move Look the ASI has nothing to do
with writing textbooks the ASI is in
charge of of
preserving and restoring our
archaeological sites it's nothing to do
with the history textbooks so let's
keep the ASI aside in this matter now
many anti-indians will resist the move
there will always be people who resist
anything you do
especially when you're trying to do
something good there is going to be a
whole lot of people who will try to
resist it now if you have a strong
government you ignore those voices and
you do what's necessary for the nation
all right that's how it is
um
so the question then is hypothetically
if I was in charge if I were in charge
of this project to rewrite the history
textbooks how would I go about this yeah
so what I would do how many states does
India have 29 28 30 uh no hate please I
don't remember how many states India has
uh let's Google it yes let's Google how
many states India has uh let us do it uh
foreign
let us go to Google uh
number of Indian
States
India's 28th States like I said and
eight union territories so let's say we
divide India yeah into 30 regions
hypothetically
just for the sake of argument
let's say we divide India into 30
regions then what I would do is in each
of these regions I would select 5 or 10
Young historians obviously you will have
to interview them and and see what kind
of knowledge they have and what the
attitude is you know the attitude is
most important because you know
typically a history graduate will be all
about dates and chronology and they will
not unders they will not focus on
chronology in the cause and effect
sequence and all that so you need to
have historians with the right mindset
the right attitude and the desire and
the understanding that history has been
written in a very distorted manner
and hopefully there should be young
people after a certain age people become
very close-minded after the age of I
don't know 30 35 or whatever 40 after a
certain age most people stop being
receptive to new ideas and stop chairs
thinking differently so you would want
young people in their mid-20s or so yeah
and what I would do is is for each state
select 5 or 10 people
and give them the task of of researching
the last let's say three thousand four
thousand years of the history of that
state from all sources available yeah
and compile a big giant book together
collaboratively
for each state
so we have 28 States let's say we divide
India into 30 States hypothetically yeah
so for each of the states I would I
would constitute a committee of of
historians
who would compile the detailed
chronological history of that state
and obviously there'll be interactions I
mean this no State exists separately no
region exists separately there's always
if everything is interconnected so
there's going to be effects from other
states and all that also coming in so I
would ask I would do this
and I would give them let's say two
years to do this so you have 10 people
from 30 30 regions so that's 300 people
and you give these people let's say two
years to do this work I think in two
years it's definitely feasible to do
this
uh so you would have to employ 300
people and you would obviously have to
have a committee that supervises what's
happening and stays on on top of
everything in tracks of the project and
all that yep
so you have 300 people working on this
and they do this for it on a two-year
two year period and you would obviously
have to pay them so let's say you're
paying them one lakh per month
why not they're doing good good work so
for each state that's 10 lakhs per month
the 30 States
that's 300 likes of three cores the
three crores per month you do that for
12 months that's 36 crores for two years
at 76 72 crores
so overall the total budget is 72 crores
and there will be obviously some
traveling and some research and all that
so about 100 crore rupees for two years
I don't think it's a lot of money for
the for the for for the central
government or whatever
and in two years you get 30 textbooks 30
textbooks that cover the detailed
history of each of these 30 regions and
then you sit to get everybody together
and based on all this detailed stuff you
create a big history of India overall
out of all of this yeah that would that
could take another one or two years so
within three four years you have not
only
a set of 30 authoritative histories of
the various parts of India you also have
one big overall history book and that's
how I would do it yeah
so I don't think it's a difficult task I
don't think it's a difficult task at all
I don't think it will take decades you
can do it in three or four years maximum
five years yeah and it will not cost a
whole lot of money
so it's definitely feasible
and it's it's about political will
if the if the political leadership is
willing to do it it can be made to
happen it's not difficult so that's how
I would go about doing this
says while researching how do you know
which information is authentic history
especially so let's understand something
when you first start
studying a subject you're a student not
a researcher right
and when you first start studying a
subject you know nothing about it you
are clueless
so you take one one textbook you start
studying it you're completely clueless
you study it and you absorb all the
information as much as you can then you
take another textbook is 38 over a
period of let's say five years you study
lots of textbooks and over time you
start understanding the patterns you
start accumulating the knowledge and if
you are intelligent enough you will
start understanding what makes sense and
where the information is kind of dodging
yeah So eventually at some point in time
you make
an imperceptible transition
from being a student to be being a
researcher
so most people unfortunately in India
consider themselves to be researchers
from day one
that's the main that's the one of the
biggest problems I see I'm a researcher
I am doing research no
spend five years or ten years as a
student show some humility have some
patience
study a lot put in the hours put in
at least several hundred hours of
reading not 700 days but several hundred
hours of active reading that's when you
have enough knowledge to make the
transition to being a researcher and
only when you have that much knowledge
can you be able to tell
what is what information is authentic or
not so it's so the ability to understand
which information is authentic and which
is not is something you have to earn by
putting in the work hundreds of hours of
study not research study
yeah
so from day one you are not a researcher
unless you have put in several hundred
hours of study you are not a researcher
and if you do put in several hundreds
hours of study then you will
automatically begin be in a position to
start telling which information is
authentic and which is not so there is
no shortcut to this I cannot tell you in
in three minutes how to figure out which
information is authentic which is not it
is something you have to earn and very
few people are willing to pay that price
that's how it goes my dear friends
Tejas says where catapults invented in
India
son of bimbisar of the harianka Dynasty
is recorded to have used catapults in in
his war against the lechovies around 480
BC Wikipedia surprisingly I'm surprised
you find it surprising
Wikipedia says it does not show this and
credits the invention of the catapults
and the mango Nails the Greeks okay I've
not taken a look at the Wikipedia
article
um but I'm not surprised that that
Wikipedia credits everything to the
Greeks yeah so was I think the second
king of the haryanka dinosaurs the son
of King bimby sir yeah the haryanka
Dynasty uh was a Dynasty uh it was a
kingdom Empire so to say in eastern
India the capital was partly Putra
the capital was was
it partly Putra was it the Raja
maybe it was a transition from I don't
remember quite quite what it was it was
in eastern India it was it was what was
later magadh so that's where the
haryanka dynasty was the the first king
was most likely bimby sir and his son
most likely was
said to have been a contemporary of uh
Gautam Buddha and also mahavir most
likely
according to the chronology that is uh
accepted in the mainstream of History
yeah so ajatru is known to have fought
uh a war against the
the confederation
which obviously as we know was led by
the lakshavi clan yeah the lechovies
were a great ancient Clan uh
the one of the who was the first major
King of the Gupta Empire
he
he had married Princess much later much
later so let's not go into that right
now yeah so uh so fought a war against
the Vegeta League which was led by the
lechevi clan and uh is known to have
conquered the Republic the mahajanapada
of vaishali and he used uh these
catapults in this war
so this happened sometime in the 5th
Century BC like 480 BC or whatever they
just said I don't remember the date yeah
um
so yeah definitely catapults were used
at the time so what is okay yeah the
question some people may have is what is
a catapult so let us uh take a look at a
catapult what is catapult
a catapult is this thing
c-a-t-a-p-u-l-t catapult it's this uh
instrument that is used in Siege Warfare
uh
uh there you go there's a Roman guy
holding a catapult so it's this
instrument on which you put these
massive stones and then you fling the
stones at fortifications so let's say
you have a fort fortified city with a
wall around it and you want to bring the
wall down you have encircled the city
with your soldiers and your army but the
wall is in impregnable and what you do
is you construct these massive machines
and you hurl this big boulders at the
wall it's like um it's like low-tech
artillery yeah
uh so that's what you had this is what a
catapult was and typically uh Wikipedia
and whatever else will say that it was
the Greeks or the Romans whoever else
that invented this thing now that's a
good example of a catapult this image
here yeah so that's a catapult
uh then if you go to wiki Wikipedia I'm
sure they will say it's out of the
Chinese or the the Greeks or the
Mesopotamians or whoever else that
invented this now think about the think
about it logically think about it
logically did ancient Indians have the
technological ability
to build something like a catapult we
know that during the so-called uh
uh so-called Peak of the Saraswati
Sindhu phase of our civilization the
so-called mature Harappan phase you had
a completely urbanized Society in India
in north northern and western and
Central India yeah
the cities were laid out according to a
grid structure you had multi-storage
buildings everywhere you had this
massive granary's massive meeting Halls
you had this massive uh uh what do you
call them public baths you had Hydro
Engineering you had uh dockyards you had
ships
and the ship is a is a complex machine
wooden instrument yeah so a civilization
that can develop all these advances in
technology can certainly develop a
catapult
and historians say that the it's known
that there is no evidence of warfare
from the entire Sarasota phase of Indian
history it's also known at the same time
that we were sending soldiers outside of
India to fight uh on behalf of our
allies in mahashi and ilam against the
arcadians 4 300 years before today yeah
so at that time we were in the most
advanced phase of the so-called Sarasota
uh civilization phase yeah extremely
advanced technology the most advanced
technology of its time where our
engineers at that time
capable of constructing catapults I
think they were catapult they were
capable of building much more complex
instruments than catapults
but catapults are made of wood and we
don't have evidence of that we don't
have any evidence of that in carvings or
paintings or whatever inscriptions and
all that so uh but also we have to
understand that the absence of evidence
like I like to say is not the evidence
of absence yeah
so um so it is recorded that ajat shatru
used uh catapults it's also known that
we had extremely advanced technology
five thousand years before today yeah so
and and at that time our our ancestors
and their our Engineers from the time
were certainly capable of of building
instruments such as catapults and much
more sophisticated instruments but we
don't have evidence so yeah what can we
say so leave Wikipedia to do its thing
we don't have to focus on Wikipedia
Wikipedia is not a reliable or
trustworthy source of information and
that's just what it is yeah
okay Road reject says Indians have been
practicing various types of dance since
ancient times did Indians export these
dances to Southeast Asian countries and
China are these dances still practiced
in these countries even to this day
uh I'm not sure if we exported any dance
forms to China but we certainly did
export a huge amount of such cultural
um
uh such culture
to the Southeast Asian region yeah for
instance uh we have something called the
apsara dance uh let's see what the
apsara dance look like it looks like it
is it is something that is still
practiced yeah the apsara dance let's go
to Google it's uh in Cambodia Etc dance
is is mostly in Cambodia
uh let's take a look at this this is
from the walls of the
Temple
so you have these ladies uh Dressed in
these uh costumes who are apsaras who
who represent the apsaras of of our
mythology
and you have these dancers who still
wear the same costumes and perform the
same dances
so these dances are clearly uh
something that most likely came out of
India
if you watch the actual videos of the
dance it's kind of reminiscent of ODC
dance and also to some extent of
manipuri classical dance yeah
so that's what you see the moves are
very graceful and they are reminiscent
of Odyssey dance and manipuri dance in
some ways then you have the the Balinese
dance
which is even more evocative of the ODC
dance form and to some extent of
kuchipudi also the facial expressions
the eye expressions and all that it kind
of reminds you of Odyssey but the
tribanga posture that you see is is
reminiscent of of odishi Dance
so this is the dance form that you have
in Bali today it's a Balinese
traditional dance form folk dance uh
classical Dance I'm not sure what you
what you call it the instruments are
also very similar to Indian instruments
the the percussion instrument the drums
and all that yeah so it's clear that uh
dance forms did
uh
were indeed exported out of India into
southeast Asia Bali is in Indonesia
Cambodia is part of the the other part
of Southeast Asia next to Vietnam and
Laos and all that so yes and you know
this is very fascinating actually I wish
our historians and sociologists would
focus on these things
and try to figure out at what stage in
our history did all these cultural
artifacts go out of India and and enter
into the into the Society of these
places it's such fascinating history and
nobody has bothered to research any of
this our historians are busy researching
or or inventing
a ways of denigrating our culture in our
history you have so much fascinating
history over here that nobody nobody is
is interested in it's really a shame so
yeah these dances are still practiced in
these countries till this day obviously
they have acquired the local flavor also
yeah
so uh you can see some elements of ODC
in there you can see some elements of
kuchipudi in there you can see some
elements of manipuri dance in there and
obviously you have the local flavor also
the local folk flavor and all that and
they typically depict the ramayan mostly
the ramayan and various other other uh
ancient events and all that so that's
what it is so yes indeed that's true
and once again Corsica is linguistically
culturally and geographically much
closer to Italy then why does France own
Corsica is a good question my friend so
let's take a look at the map
where is a Corsica
let's go to the map where is our dear
good friend the map
and where is korthika
so let's go to the Mediterranean Sea yes
and over here we have Italy As We Know
and uh over here we have France and here
is what they call cars and south of
course we have Sardinia the main city in
sardines which is part of Italy near
this big island over here is part of
Italy and this island Here Is Corsica
the French call it which is very close
to Italy and yet it's part of France and
therefore the the question naturally
arises is is to why is Corsica a part of
France even though it's linguistically
culturally Etc geographically much
closer to Italy
so where is Genoa Genoa is the city here
there you have it so
Corsica the island was controlled was
only could say by the Republic of Genoa
for about 400 500 years until the 18th
century yeah
so Genoa was this city state you could
say the Republic of Genoa Italy was not
always with this one nation yeah yeah
they had the various phases of India of
Italian History so Genoa was a very
powerful City a very powerful Republic
at one time and it essentially
controlled or owned Corsica until the
18th century and then there was this
then what happened is that uh there was
this Treaty of Versailles not the 20th
century Treaty of Versa but the 18th
century Treaty of Versailles in
1768. so in the according to this treaty
Corsica was was given away was seated to
France by the Republic of Genoa as per
this Treaty of Versailles in
1768. now why why was it like this so
Corsica
um
so essentially what what happened is
that the French desired to own Corsica
so as to have a bigger uh geopolitical
or geostrategic or Naval footprint in
the Mediterranean Sea and the general
ways were in need of money and they had
become weaker weakened because of
whatever reason yeah
you know things change that's the main
thing in history so Genoa had become
much weaker and they were in need of
money the French offered them money they
said will not go to war we'll just pay
you money and give us Corsica yeah so
that's what happened and and the general
ways sold Corsica just like the Russians
sold Alaska to America the same way the
genois sold Corsica to France in 1768.
funnily enough not funnily enough but
coincidentally the year after the
Genovese sold Corsica to France
they sold it in 1768 in 1769 was the
birth of napoleone parte in Corsica yeah
he was born in Corsica
and uh
his father
was fighting a guerrilla war against the
French he was not willing to accept
Corsica becoming a part of France so he
was fighting a freedom struggle
Napoleon's father against the French in
Corsica yeah and eventually he kind of
he was a practical man then he made his
peace with friends and he even became
you could say the the ambassador of
Corsica in the French Court in Paris uh
Etc and through his connections he was
able to enlist Napoleon his son in a
good military school and then as you say
the rest is history within 20 years
Napoleon was the emperor of France
that's how it it went in in between
there was also the the small issue of
the French Revolution that happened
that's how it was so the Italians owned
Corsica the the Genovese owned Corsica
and they chose to sell it to France and
that benefited France a great deal and
as a result of that Corsica is still
part of France interesting
story
Shri kesari says Serbia has recently
revoked visa on arrival that facility
for Indians it was the only European
nation to provide visa on arrival to
India is this attempt of Serbia to join
the Schengen region Visa or failure of
India's engagement with Serbia or is it
a problem of illegal immigration okay
yes until the end of 2022 Indians could
just fly to Serbia and they would be
given a visa on arrival once they
arrived at Belgrade airport or wherever
it is that they arrived where is Serbia
let's take a look at the map once again
where is the map so we know where Italy
is yeah this is Italy here Italy yes and
if you go east of Italy you have the
Balkan region you have Croatia then you
have Bosnia and Herzegovina and then you
have cro then you have Serbia and uh the
Serbian capital is Belgrade yep
so
um what's happened is that Serbia wishes
to join the European Union it is
currently in advanced stages of
negotiation
for joining the European Union and the
Schengen area yeah and one of the
preconditions for Serbia joining the EU
is for Serbia to start uh adhering to EU
Visa regulations
so uh the European Union has a very
uniform set of Visa regulations it's a
Visa for his own so once you have a visa
to any Schengen country you are you are
free to travel in the entire region
that's how it is
uh so Serbia wants to become part of
that and that's why they have to now
start uh adhering to whatever Visa
regulations the EU countries have and
for the EU EU countries there is no visa
on arrival for India because India
belongs to a category where they do not
wish to offer a visa on arrival for
Americans there is without arrival any
time but not for Indians so until until
December 31 2022 survey I was offering
Indians a visa on arrival now they are
no longer doing that it's not because of
some kind of failure of India's
government to engage with Serbia it's
because of Serbia's desire to join the
European Union and the European Union
says that these are the rules you want
to join us this is what you have to do
so that's what they are doing
all right and they say it's about
illegal immigration it's not only about
India but other countries also which
which were uh given the visa on arrival
facility which has now been revoked not
only India but other some other nations
as well so uh the pretext is illegal
immigration blah blah blah all that it
doesn't matter who cares yeah so that's
how it is so it's not because of some
failure of Indian diplomacy or
engagement it's none of that it's just
because the serbians want to join the
European Union that's why this has
happened unfortunate but that's how it
goes how it goes in the world yes
says what are the LaGrange points in
space and what kind of telescope is Elon
Musk building
LaGrange points Let's uh let's put that
on the screen because it's visually it
makes much more sense visually there are
five LaGrange points which these are
equilibrium points let me put that on
the screen so that you understand yeah
visually it's much much more easier to
understand okay
uh
crunch points so you have L1 to L5 let's
go to the images uh let's see a good
image this one is good one yeah
so we have the Earth Sun System over
here
this here is the Earth this bright point
at the center is the Sun and then you
have L1 L2 L3 L4 and L5 the five
LaGrange points so the L1 LaGrange point
is an equilibrium point between the
Earth and the Sun yeah we can calculate
the distance if you place an object over
there it will be in in complete perfect
equilibrium it will not go anywhere else
it will stay in its place if you place
an object on the L at the L1 LaGrange
point it is between the Earth and the
Sun it's where the gravitational effects
of both objects the Earth and the Sun
cancel each other out
the L2 LaGrange point is in a straight
line between the earth of the Sun but it
is at the point where the Earth obscures
the Sun's light
so it's on the other side yeah and over
there also you can place you can you can
park spacecraft in in that place or in
orbit around the L2 point the James Webb
Space Telescope is right now parked in
an orbit around the L2 LaGrange point so
the L2 point is also a point of
equilibrium
between in the Earth's sun system the L3
point is on the other side of the Sun so
I would never recommend you do this but
if you were to hypothetically stare at
the sun then on the other side of the
sun you have the L3 LaGrange Point yeah
that's also an equilibrium point where
you can park some spacecraft or a planet
in orbit and you will never get to see
it then you have the L4 and L5 LaGrange
points so The L4 and L5 points are the
uh they if you see the Earth and Sun
system and The L4 point then this forms
an equilateral triangle a triangle whose
three angles are all 60 degrees
so that's The L4 and L5 LaGrange points
you can even Park spacecraft or
satellites or whatever in those points
as well so the LaGrange points are
something you have with every object in
the solar system not only the Earth
Jupiter has its LaGrange points and and
that's where you have this huge Bunches
of asteroids that are parked over there
the Trojan asteroids yeah Trojan asked
uh as the roads
so Trojan asteroids
so if you see in this image Jupiter has
these two bunches of asteroids that go
around with it or which are parked in
The L4 and L5 LaGrange points of Jupiter
which are called the Trojan points I
believe yeah
uh so that's so in that Way Jupiter is
able to uh Shield Earth from the impacts
of those asteroids which would otherwise
be free to go around and and cause havoc
in the solar system yeah
so that's The L4 and L5 Trojan asteroids
of Jupiter so that's what LaGrange
points are now the other question that
balram
has asked is that uh what kind of
telescope is Elon Musk building so Elon
Musk is not building a telescope He is
building various more and more powerful
Rockets uh the most powerful rocket is
building right now is called the
Starship I believe yeah the Starship
which is a massive giant rocket which
has twice the amount of thrust that the
Saturn V rocket had the one that took
the first human beings to the moon in
the 1960s
that was until now I believe the most
powerful rocket ever built and the
Starship that Elon Musk the SpaceX is
building is twice as powerful yep so
Elon Musk has said that you could use
the Starship as a saddle as a telescope
of its own you know the Starship let's
take a look at the Starship We Don't the
SpaceX Starships a space X
Space X star
ship
give me a second let me put that on
screen
so this is what the rocket looks like
the SpaceX Starship as you can see it's
pretty much cylindrical in shape more or
less so Elon Musk says that you could
use this rocket that the cylindrical
design of Etc as the the structure that
that encases a telescope so it could
have like 10 times the resolution of the
Hubble Space Telescope so that's what he
has proposed and obviously it's just a
proposal it's not like he's building it
but it's certainly feasible you put this
thing in Earth orbit and then you put
these giant lenses in it and start using
it as a telescope it will work perfectly
well yeah
so that's what he's proposing
so he's not right now building a
telescope this space uh this rocket has
not been
tested yet fully I believe it's not uh
yet gone into Earth orbit but it's
certainly going to happen sooner or
later and then if the funding is made
available Etc you could have a giant
telescope inside one of these Rockets
orbiting the Earth so right now we have
a two major
space-based telescopes one is the old
Hubble Space Telescope that went into
orbit in the 1980s late 80s and then you
have the newer telescope the much more
advanced uh James Webb's business scope
which is parked at the uh L2 LaGrange
Point yeah
uh and then you could have a new
telescope if Elon musk's Musk gets the
funding and he has also proposed that he
could uh extend the life of the Hubble
Space Telescope by uh so right now the
Hubble Space Telescope uh it was it a
few years ago I think it was placed into
an elevated orbit around the Earth at
about 560 kilometers above the surface
of the Earth yeah and in the past few
years it's it's dropped it's its
altitude has dropped or elevation has
dropped by about 20 or 30 kilometers So
eventually it's going to come closer to
the Earth's atmosphere it's going to
start experiencing an atmospheric drag
and eventually it will have to be
brought into the atmosphere and burned
out that's what it eventually will
happen so it is possible that Elon Musk
could use his Dragon SpaceX Dragon
capsule spacecraft to go and service the
Hubble Space Telescope and again put it
in a higher orbit which could extend the
lifestyle lifetime of the Hubble
telescope by another decade or two
possibly yeah it's not a bad idea and
it's certainly something that's feasible
if NASA if the US government is willing
to put in the money so that's what Elon
Musk is doing or could be doing he could
first of all extend the life span of the
Hubble Space Telescope by another decade
or so if he does this if it is approved
and secondly if the funding is made
available he could turn he could
transform one of his Starship Rockets
into a giant telescope with maybe 10
times the resolution of the Hubble Space
Telescope so that is what is going on
right now yes
right
do submarines go through the Swiss Canal
considering the fact that they need to
stay hidden or do they go through the
long route so you know what does a Suez
Canal look like let's take a look at
that
Suez Channel
let's put that on the screen
give me a second
Swiss canal
so this is what the source kind of looks
like so the Swiss Canal is pretty wide
it can even take a as you can see in
aircraft carrier an aircraft carrier can
easily easily go to the Swiss canal
so if a ship
of the size of an aircraft carrier
can uh go through the Swiss Canal
um a submarine can certainly go through
the canal as well
so the width of the sewers Canal is
about 200 to 220 meters and you can see
that in this image that is on the screen
right now yeah
uh there's here's another image of an
aircraft carrier transiting uh through
the sewage Canal so the width of the
canal is more than 200 meters the depth
is about 23 to 24 meters
the depth of the source Canal now let's
take a look at what a Los Angeles class
submarine looks like lost Angeles class
submarine one of them is called the USS
Annapolis right
so here is a schematic representation of
the of a typical Los Angeles class
submarine so you have this black portion
on top the the top half and you have the
red portion the bottom half yeah
so uh the Los Angeles class submarine is
the uh most prevalent class of American
nuclear submarine I think more than 20
of the submarines are still operational
right now yeah uh so the submarine has a
beam which is the width uh I'm not sure
what the beam is and what the width is
let's go to Wikipedia and find out what
the beam and the width is the beam and
the draft is
Los Angeles class submarine
uh 26 are active 34 are retired the
length is 37362 feet that's 110 meters
that's the length we don't care about
that the beam
uh is 10 meters which is how wide the
submarine is yeah and the draft is nine
point let's say it's 10 meters that is
the uh
the distance from the bottom of the
submarine to the water line okay so if
you take this example the red portion
is
the draft of the submarine and that's
about 10 meters
so that is if the submarine was was
visible in the water half of it would be
still submerged that's the red portion
and that red portion is about 10 meters
tall
and obviously the the dark portion the
black portion is also about 10 meters
tall but then you have the Corning Tower
which could be another 15 meters so it's
about 25 meters plus 10 meters it's
about 35 meters total in in height that
the submarine has so clearly with the
depth of the sewers Canal being 20 23
meters 24 meters it's impossible for a
submarine to pass through it submerged
impossible
so a submarine can certainly pass
through the sewers Canal but it is
impossible for a submarine of this this
size or most likely any size to stay
submerged and to stay hidden it will
have to be visible and that's the deal
that's how it is so I think in the past
American submarines have transited
through the sewers canal in the past I'm
sure Israeli submarines also must have
granted the Sewells canal and uh so the
source Canal is not meant for you know
stealthy navigation uh it's it's
whatever happens there is is essentially
something that's that everybody gets to
see yeah that's how it is
okay Muhammad Adil says how can I as a
student study Physics more effectively
and please suggest some effective steps
to become a scientist
uh how can you study Physics more
effectively first of all it's all about
mathematics you want to be a good
physicist you have to have a very strong
foundation in mathematics in calculus in
linear algebra and differential
equations and and all that which comes
with it take a good book uh mathematical
methods of physics but marry Bose or or
whoever else it is I've got a few over
here and the various subjects you know
to master so you need to have a very
strong foundation in mathematics that is
non-negotiable you want to be a good
uh you want to be really Adept at
physics you have to first of all master
mathematics and then
to understand the various concepts of
physics into internalize internalize
them you have to work through lots of
problems you to solve lots of physics
problems yeah and you first understand
the key Concepts and principles of
physics by reading textbooks Maybe by by
looking at diagrams and animations Maybe
by watching by by using online resources
like videos and all that yeah you
understand the concepts from that and
then you apply that in solving problems
you have to solve hundreds maybe
thousands of problems to internalize all
these Concepts it should be like part of
you you know living breathing sleeping
physics you also have to understand the
experimental basis of physics so how
where all the experiments performed that
gave us all this data and all of this
information yeah that will give you a
deeper understanding of the subject
then you try and relate the concepts
that you have learned to real world
situations take a look at a crystal why
does a crystal look like this a crystal
has certain properties where do these
properties come from that's an example
and so on so forth you know so try and
relate whatever you've learned all this
concept that you've mastered to real
world situations because that will help
you make the the material more relatable
and understand it better and practice
practice practice
solve as many problems as you possibly
can that is the key to mastering physics
so that's how you study Physics more
effectively yeah if you really want to
study it properly and master the subject
now how do you become a scientist so
once you have studied and mastered the
subject you have all this knowledge and
understanding you can use it in two ways
or three ways one is you do nothing with
it that's a waste of time the other way
so there are two real ways of using it
most people who really master physics
use it in two ways one is they teach the
subject to others so they become
teachers or professors
that's what you do when you have
mastered the subject but you want to
communicate that and transmit that
knowledge to others the other thing you
can do with your knowledge is to solve
is to try and solve unsolved problems
that's when you become an actual
scientist a scientist is a person
who solves problems who tries to solve
problems that are still unsolved that's
where you become a scientist just
knowing physics doesn't make you a
scientist not a physicist yeah you have
to actually work on problems and
problems that are still open problems
that's what you do
so first you have to really Master the
subject by going through the steps that
I outlined and then you have to pick up
problems that are still open problems
there are lots of open
problems in physics that nobody has an
answer for you right now you take those
problems and you try to solve them
that's that's called research active
research and that's how you become a
scientist and obviously if you want to
be a scientist you will be you'll need
to have degrees and all that yeah
master's degree PhD whatever and you
will have to be in in a scientific
institution you can also do it as an
independent scientist but it's much
harder if you go through along that
route yeah because obviously if you are
if you are in an institution in an
Institute you get you have the funding
you have the job security and you're the
time and all that otherwise you don't so
that's how you do it and that's how you
become a scientist I I hope that uh kind
of throws some light clarifies it yeah
right
says why are Central America and South
America still poor even though most of
these countries are pro-usa well even
the Philippines is pro-usa it is very
poor it's a third world nation that's
what the Americans call it
Pakistan has been pro-usa for the
longest period they are desperately poor
there are so many African nations that
have been pro-us for the longest time
they are desperately poor so this
hopefully will explain tell you that
being pro-usa is not a ticket to
becoming rich
just because I am Pro USA doesn't mean
that I'll become rich that doesn't
that's not how it works yeah which
nations are rich which are pro-usa Japan
and South Korea and Taiwan and why are
these nations rich Let's go to the map
where is the map the map is eluding me I
need to capture it and place it on the
screen here it is yes
so the Nations
that are indeed Rich are Taiwan in South
Korea and Japan these three nations are
under large-scale permanent U.S
occupation there are tens of thousands
of U.S troops in these places and when
you have where you have so many
Americans
permanently stationed in these places
they want the place to be nice and clean
and pretty and developed so they have
ensured that Japan and South Korea and
Taiwan become highly developed
they don't have any permanent prisons in
the Philippines so they don't they don't
care what happens there they don't care
what happens in the various African
nations which are pro-usa and so on and
so forth that's how it goes so just
being Pro USA is not a ticket to
financial riches and freedom and all
that yeah they get it
it's not it's not as simple as that
right balram said I used to read a lot
but suddenly I quit
because then I realized that I'm not
able to apply the knowledge in my life
I'm really struggling please guide me
you know if you read a lot it doesn't
mean you're gonna succeed in life
if you read all kinds of random stuff
you read a few novels here you read some
non-fiction there you need some read
something else here and so on so forth
it's it's not going to help you in any
way whatsoever in life you will
accumulate a lot of knowledge
information perhaps
but it's not going to help you in life
reading doesn't change your life in any
way whatsoever unless unless there's a
caveat here
unless it's focused reading and focused
learning and then you apply it
yeah so let's say you are a business you
are you're an entrepreneur you want to
start a business and you have a budget
of let's say 10 lakh for the year yeah
so then if you read specific books
about how to bootstrap a small business
and things like that
then and then you try things in life
in your business then you may be able to
apply it
so your application has to be specific
and focused just there are people who
read all their life and they do nothing
in life
so if you want to do something in life
you have to take action reading is not
action reading is passive
yeah so first of all you need to be
proactive in life you need to have a
goal you need to be working towards the
goal and you have to be willing to fail
and your initial failures five six
failures should be small failures not a
huge failures not catastrophic failures
let's say you have a budget of 10 lakh
Rupees and you risk it all you don't
understand risk management yeah
your first failure should not be your
last failure so bad that you can not
ever try business again yeah you just
fail in small increments and you love
you to learn each time from the failure
and that in that's where reading comes
in so how to learn from failure how to
apply various principles in business so
that's just one example I'm offering you
when it comes to sport
if you want to achieve success in sport
you can read about mental management you
know people there are people who are
extremely talented but the joke at the
wrong minute wrong wrong time all the
time in sport certain sports teams are
are notorious for choking so how to
manage the mental aspect of sport that's
what you can read so you can only apply
knowledge in life that you have read
about when you're reading from a
specific perspective when you're reading
specific specific knowledge you read
random stuff you read a little bit of
History you read a little bit of science
you read some some novels you read
something else it's not going to help
you your reading should be focused and
you have to apply those conception
principles and whatever you're doing
yeah
so that's how you do it and uh
so yeah all the best
trupti says how do you raise your
standards
and also how to increase confidence and
self-esteem raising your standards means
improving yourself every day
or over a period of time yeah small
gradual incremental changes improve
improve improve improve whatever you're
doing
that's essentially how we raise the
standards there are so many ways of
doing it stop wasting your time stop
watching Netflix stop scrolling through
Instagram seven hours a day people do
that that's a very simple way of raising
a standard stop doing that go on a diet
you know social media diet only 30
minutes a day maximum or whatever works
for you and then use the remaining time
in something that is actually productive
and that's gonna take you somewhere
that's how you raise your standards and
then build good habits yeah
we'll build build habits that that take
you in the right direction uh stop
wasting time stop talking too much there
are so many I mean this this habit among
Indians
Indians talk Indians argue so much
Indians not just Indians most people
it's not just Indians that would be
wrong to say most people talk too much
most people argue too much most people
never listen
talk talk talk so that's something if if
that's that describes you then you can
change try to change that yeah so
there's so much you can do to raise your
standards yeah don't tolerate mediocrity
don't tolerate tolerate the average try
and rise above the average
try and be better than everybody around
you that's how you raise your standards
so you just identify specific things in
which you want to be better now how do
you increase confidence and service team
it's not easy but one of the easiest
ways of doing it is to never make a
promise you can't keep and whatever you
say you will do do it
it's it's not always possible to succeed
in that yes but you have to strive to do
that you have to strive to do that so
never make a promise you are not
capable of keeping and secondly whatever
you say that you will do go ahead and do
it and you keep doing this over and over
again your confidence and self-esteem
will automatically arise that's how you
do it that's like some simple tips all
right now let's briefly take some
questions from the live chat because uh
I seem to have covered most of what I
took today but yeah
all right so if you have any questions
you can ask me right now and I will take
I will try and take a few
questions from the live chat
yes I have a question since childhood
says Nilesh why does the universe exist
and what would be there or happen if the
universe doesn't exist well I have no
answer to that only only
God would have an answer to that if a
God does exist who has created the
universe why does the universe exist you
you ask 15 people they will give you 15
different answers there is no scientific
uh
way of answering it because we don't
know what's outside if there is anything
outside and what created the universe
and why was it created we have no idea
no scientists not even Albert Einstein
or or Isaac Newton or ramanujan can
answer that question it's purely
hypothetical purely it's all conjecture
so we don't know I I definitely don't
know it's it's beyond my my knowledge my
my small amount of knowledge cannot
answer this question I have no idea why
the universe exists and what would be
there or happen if it would not exist I
I am too small uh an entity one such a
such a big question but it's it's good
you have this question you know it shows
that the thinking process is there and
it's a it's it's a good thought to have
um
all right
Ice Age coming or it's just a myth we
will see anything could happen you know
there's 4.2 kilo year event happened
nobody knew it was coming but it came
and there was this uh
what was it called the younger driest
event a thousand years of Ice Age it
happened all of a sudden most likely
because of a an impact event so these
things are what you would call Black
Swan events you have no idea they're
coming in this really come uh so yeah so
right now we're talking about global
warming and all but who knows something
could happen and it could cause an ice
age is is possible yes
uh
why does time pass faster as we turn
older
that's an interesting phenomenon yes uh
when you're a kid when you're a small
kid like three years old
one day seems to take a an eternity one
day is a very long event when you're a
small toddler three four years old but
when you are 20 a day seems to pass
faster when you're 30 it seems so fast
pass faster than older people in the 70s
and 80s say that the time is just flying
away now you know so yeah it's it's a
phenomenon that see that is definitely
there and it looks like uh the more
experiences we accumulate the more
things seem to be the same and when
there is so much sameness time seems to
pass faster but when you would expect
experiencing something very different
and very new that's when time again
seems to slow down
so it's it's a thing of perception and
uh maybe that's why maybe that's why
time seems to pass faster so the the
trick is if you want time to pass slower
get yourself into experiences no you've
not experienced before
and things that are different then
things then that time will seem to pass
slower
um
what else do we have ah hey
please explain Battle of 10 things
already done sir please look at my older
videos do a little search
search
I've already done it
the thing is this I have got more than a
thousand video clips on this channel
I've answered almost every question
imaginable obviously I still get
questions that I've never answered
before so that's great so I'm really
grateful for that but there are lots of
questions I've already answered so so
you you take the time to type a question
and put it over here in the comments you
can take the same time to put it in the
search box on my channel and you may get
a video clip that in which I've already
answered the question so to do do try
that yeah
okay let's take one more question before
we are done I can see a million uh
am I in atheist I think atheists are
complete idiots with all due respect
they are completely idiots so no I'm not
with all due respect all due respect uh
please don't get upset and emotional and
all that I'm just kidding I am kidding
here yes with all due respect
uh
I never spoke about Pangea I must have
spoken about panji it was this
hypercontinent or everything all the
landmasses stuck together about how when
was it 300 million years before today or
something like that yep so there you
have it I have spoken about Pangea
and uh is there anything else that I
could take now
uh I am woke yes
congratulations you are woke
congratulations
huh
I
my thoughts on erdogan's Turkey well
Advanced turkey is going backwards it's
going it's turned its back on the ideals
and principles of Mustafa Kemal Ataturk
and it's going back into the ottoman era
maybe maybe Shri erdogan wants to
recreate the Ottoman Empire so yeah
that's what I can say in brief
it obviously uh is a nation that has a
imperialistic
Imperial Ambitions yeah Neo Imperial
Ambitions it considers itself a nation
or or an Empire that has been wronged
and they want to recreate the regain
what they have lost so it looks like the
Turks are on their paths here
okay
all right I guess we are at the end of
today's session two hours ten minutes
plus so thank you very much for all the
questions it's always great fun talking
to you all and let's keep doing this all
right so I will see you in next week's
live streams and until then take care of
yourselves
and see you soon thank you bye